Finding Aid for the Collection of Material about the History of Photography LSC.0092
UCLA Library Special Collections
History of Photography collection of material
1840-1917
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0092
1 oversize box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942327883606533
Scope and Content
Collection consists of examples showing the development of photography from daguerreotypes to Velox prints. Includes ambrotypes, tintypes, albumens, cabinet portraits, and a cyanotype. Also includes a group of prints made from copy negatives of holdings in the Historical Collection of the Royal Photographic Society, London. Photographers include Eadward Muybridge, William Henry Fox Talbot, Julia Margaret (Pattle) Cameron, and Gertrude Käsebier.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Examples of photography (Box 1).
Prints made from copy negatives in the Historical Collection of the Royal Photographic Society, London (Box 2).
Oversize group of prints from copy negatives of above (Oversize box).
Items Removed from Collection
1. Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904. 2 items. Triple-oversize photographs from copy negatives are shelved with ***TR/16.8/M98 an 1887. Muybridge, Eadweard. Animal Locomotion, 1872-1887. Available at the Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
Photography -- History -- Archives.; Royal Photographic Society of Great Britain
- Examples of Photographs
  - Daguerreotypes., 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    1. Daguerreotype 1/6th plate: girl in striped dress, badly scratched inner case covered with tweed; image sealed with scotch tape.
    2. Daguerreotype 1/6th plate: girl in carved chair; cleaned case needs rehinging.
    3. Splendid 1/4th plate in unusual frame; portrait of young girls.
  - Ambrotypes., 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    4. Ambrotype 1/9th plate: very good, backed with cloth, but emulsion protected by glass.
    5. Ambrotyype 1/6th plate: interesting patriotic protector frame; example of deterioration from cloth cacking.
    6. Ambrotype 1/4th plate: uncased; painted backing, asphaltum.
    7. Ambrotype 1/9th plate on ruby glass.
  - Tintypes., 13 items. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    8. Tintype: full plate portrait, tinted.
    9. Tintype: full plate group portrait in buggy.
    10-11. Tintypes 1/6th plates: very good portraits.
    12-14. Tintypes 1/6th plates in paper jackets.
    15-17. Tintypes 1/6th plates: ordinary.
    18. Tintype 1/9th plate in paper sleeve with ad on verso.
    19. Tintype damaged from cleaning.
    20. Tintype in paper jacket: gem.
  - Albumen prints., 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    21. Albumen: full print view of exterior of mosque.
    22-23. Albumens: portraits mounted on oval cardboard backings.
  - Cartes-de-visites., 8 items. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    24-20. Various portraits: ordinary, most have document stamp on verso.
    31. Portrait in paper frame.
  - Gelatin cabinets and other portraits., 11 items. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    32-36. Cabinet portraits: ordinary.
    37. Imperial (10 × 7 in.).
    38. Cabinet portrait on larger mount (7.25 × 5 in.).
    39. Cabinet portrait on larger mount (8.25 × 7.75 in.).
    40. Group portrait, 5 × 7 in. mount.
    41. Portrait on 10.75 × 8 in. mount.
    42. Velox portrait.
  - Miscellaneous photographs., 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    43. Kodak no.1 photograph.
    44. Gelatin 8 × 10 in. mount: view of house.
    45. Cyanotype 8 × 10 in.: two children in garden.
- A Group of Prints Made from Copy Negatives of Holdings in the Historical Collection of the Royal Photographic Society, London
  - Adamson and Hill., 15 items. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annan, James Craig, 1864-1946., 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Carnarvon, Henry Howard Molyneux Herbert, 4th earl of, 1830-1890., 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Coburn, Alvin Langdon, 1882-1966., 6 items. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Davison, George, 1856-1930., 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Day, F. Holland, 1864-1933., 6 items. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Demachy, Robert, d. 1937., 8 items. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Evans, Frederick Henry, 1852-1943., 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fenton, Roger, 1819-1896., 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Molard, Humbert de, d. 1874., 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904., 10 items. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Polak, Richard, b. 1870., 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Rejlander, Oscar Gustave, 1813-1875., 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Robinson, Henry Peach, 1830-1901., 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sutcliffe, Frank Meadow, 1853-1941., 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Talbot, William Henry Fox, 1800-1877., 10 items. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Thomson, John, 1837-1921., 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - White, Clarence Hudson, 1871-1925., 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Wilkinson, Benjamin Gay, 1857-1927., 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Oversize group of prints made from copy negatives. (Box 1)
    1. Cameron, Julia Margaret (Pattle) 1815-1879. 25 items.
    2. Carnarvon, Henry Howar Molyneux Herbert, 4th earl of, 1830-1890. 1 item.
    3. Coburn, Alvin Langdon, 1882-1966. 3 items.
    4. Day, F. Holland, 1864-1933. 2 items.
    5. Emerson, Peter Henry, 1856-1936. 1 item.
    6. Fenton, Roger, 1819-1896. 1 item.
    7. Käsebier, Gertrude, 1852-1934. 1 item.
    8. Keighley, Alexander, 1861-1947. 1 item.
    9. Konc, Olga. 1 item.
    10. Mortimer, F.J., d. 1944. 4 items.
    11. Rejlander, Oscar Gustave, 1813-1875. 1 item.
    12. Sawyer, Lyddell, 1856-1895. 1 item.
    13. Talbot, William Henry Fox, 1800-1877. 5 items.
    14. Unidentified photograph. 1 item.